Marie Munk Papers, 1901-1976
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Marie Munk Papers
1901-1976
Munk, Marie, 1885-1978
MS 111
13 boxes (4.5 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Lawyer, judge, and marriage counselor. The Marie Munk papers include correspondence, writings, and memorabilia. The collection documents her work on domestic relations, marriage counseling, juvenile delinquency, and women's rights. Of special interest are manuscripts, written in both English and German, on the position of women before and after World War I; her experiences as a judge in pre-Hitler Germany; and an oral history conducted at Smith College in 1971.
Biographical Note
Marie Munk was born in Berlin (then Prussia) on July 4, 1885. She graduated from Kaiserin Augusta Gymnasium and received her Doctor of Laws degree from Heidelberg University in 1911. Having passed the two necessary bar exams in 1920 and 1924, Munk began work with the Prussian Ministry of Justice. In 1925 she became the first woman admitted to practice law in Berlin and was appointed District Court Judge in 1929. Because she was of Jewish descent, by Nazi law she was dismissed in 1933. Munk first visited the United States in 1933 at the invitation of the International Federation of Business and Professional Women as a delegate to the International Congress of Women in Chicago. She returned in 1934, having secured a position at the New York School for Delinquent Girls. In 1943 Munk was admitted to the Massachusetts Bar. She went on to work as a marriage counselor for the Court of Common Pleas in Toledo, Ohio, then settled permanently in Cambridge, Massachusetts i
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Marie Munk papers consist 4 linear feet of correspondence, writings, printed material and memorabilia. There is documentation of Munk's early career in articles from the U.S. and Germany, and in personal and business correspondence. Although there are some letters from her brother (1914-1915), most correspondence dates from 1934. Of particular interest are letters from musicologist Sophie Drinker (1952-66). There are numerous publications by Munk, as well as manuscripts in both German and English, including material on domestic relations, marriage and marriage counseling, juvenile delinquency, and women's rights. Of special interest are manuscripts on the position of women before and after World War I, written for the International Federation of Business and Professional Women; Munk's reminiscences of her experiences as a judge in pre-Hitler Germany (1945); and a proposal by Munk to reunify East and West Berlin (1948).
Organization of the Collection
This collection is organized into five series:
I. Biographical Material
II. Correspondence
III. Writings
IV. Subjects
V. Organizations
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
History of the Collection
The Marie Munk Papers were originally bequeathed to the Sophia Smith Collection and the Schlesinger Library. It was determined that the entire collection was more appropriate to the Sophia Smith Collection due to the substantial content on Germany, and the Schlesinger Library transferred their portion of the papers to the SSC in 1979.
Search Terms
Behl, Wofgang, 1918-; Drinker, Sophie Hutchinson, 1888-1968; Munk, Marie, 1885-1978; Female juvenile delinquents--United States--History--Sources; Feminism--Germany--History--20th century--Sources; Immigrants--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Jewish women--Germany--History--20th century--Sources; Women judges--Germany--History--Sources; Women lawyers--United States--History--Sources; World War, 1914-1918--Germany--Women; World War, 1914-1918--Germany--Personal narratives; Women--Germany--Social conditions--Sources; Marriage--United States--History--20th century--Sources
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIAL (1901-1975), 1 linear ft.
  This series contains poetry, photographs, scrapbooks, clippings, and official documents. In addition, there is documentation of Munk's early career in articles from the U. S. and Germany, autobiographical sketches, and an oral history conducted at Smith College in 1971.
- SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE (1914-1977), 1.5 linear ft.
  This series is organized into to subseries: Personal and Business. The bulk of the material is post-1934, following Munk's arrival in the United States. It includes six letters from mucsicologist Sophie Drinker (1952, 1965-66). The only personal correspondence remaining from her life in Germany are World War I letters from her brother, Ernest Munk, to his family (1914-15).
- SERIES III. WRITINGS (1915-1964), 1.25 linear ft.
  This series consists of numerous publications and manuscripts in both German and English. Topics include domestic relations, marriage and marriage counseling, juvenile delinquency, and women's rights. There is also a manuscript of an unpublished book, "Elements of Love and Marriage" (1950). Of special interest are the manuscripts on the position of women during and after World War I (1940), written for the International Federation of Business and Professional Women, her reminiscences of her experiences as a judge in pre-Hitler Germany (1945), and a proposal for the reunification of Berlin.
- SERIES IV. SUBJECTS (1918-1959), .5 linear ft.
  The series contains printed material and manuscripts pertaining to several subject areas, particularly domestic relations, illegitimacy, juvenile delinquency, psychology, Germany, and Women. Also of interest is a manuscript by Kate Lindenau about women during World War I and the postwar period.
- SERIES V. ORGANIZATIONS (1931-1974), .25 linear ft.
  This series has in it membership records and printed material related to Munk's organizational affiliations.
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIAL (1901-1975)
  - Material relating to the Marie Munk Papers (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Clippings 1924-27, 1936-56, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Biographical information and publication lists 1911-12, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Oral history by Betty Eberhart 1971 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Poem's written for her grandfather Wilhelm Munk's birthday and death 1914-29 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Munk family poems and plays 1914, 1935, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Memorabilia and unidentified material 1936-76, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Photographs 1934-40, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Official documents
    - College and university diplomas 1904-23, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Certificates 1901-22, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Letters of recommendation 1919-43 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Papers re: admission to Ohio Bar 1944 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Will 1967 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Photocopies of material from scrapbook 1917-47 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
  - Scrapbook 1933-47 (Box 3)
- SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE (1914-1977)
  - Personal
    - Outgoing
      - A-Kcirca 1965-76 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Ackerman, J. 1965-75 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - Arner, Charlotte 1970 (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - Behl, Lula and Wolfgang 1968-70 (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - Braun, Louise 1972-76 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - Drinker, Sophie 1952-66 (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - Egbers, Marlis and Gerhard 1967-75 (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - Engelbrecht, Hertha 1967-75 (Box 4, Folder 8)
      - Fields, Sue 1965-75 (Box 4, Folder 9)
      - "Friends, Dear" 1945, 1951, 1965-77 (Box 4, Folder 10)
      - Gans, Helene 1965-76 (Box 4, Folder 11)
      - Gerson, Tove 1965-76 (Box 4, Folder 12)
      - Glucksman, Elisabeth 1940, 1965-75, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 13)
      - Gottschalk, Julia 1955-69 (Box 4, Folder 14)
      - Hahn, Beate 1967-70 (Box 4, Folder 15)
      - Haupt, Gerda 1968-77 (Box 4, Folder 16)
      - Heim, Julia 1909-10, 1966-74 (Box 4, Folder 17)
      - von Hentig, Otto 1966-76 (Box 4, Folder 18)
      - Howalt, Carola 1964-77 (Box 4, Folder 19)
      - Kuhn, Craig and Sally 1971-74 (Box 4, Folder 20)
      - L-Zcirca 1962-76 (Box 4, Folder 21)
      - Leonard, Louisa 1965-76 (Box 4, Folder 22)
      - Lindenau, Kathelien 1963-77, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 23)
      - Mayer, Erna 1968-69 (Box 4, Folder 24)
      - Mombert, Francois and Margot 1966-75 (Box 4, Folder 25)
      - Mueller-Munk, Gertrude (sister) 1964-69 (Box 4, Folder 26)
      - Mueller-Munk, Peter (nephew) 1961-67 (Box 4, Folder 27)
      - Mueller-Zemmerick, Ingeburg 1968-76 (Box 4, Folder 28)
      - Reynolds, Elizabeth 1970-76 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - Runne, Ursula 1967-75 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      - Schoenheintz, Maria 1967-69 (Box 5, Folder 3)
      - Theil, Ursel 1971-75 (Box 5, Folder 4)
      - Thompson, Lisbet 1955-75 (Box 5, Folder 5)
      - Yarke, Gerta 1965-74 (Box 5, Folder 6)
      - Unidentified (Doerchen and Ferdinand) 1966-76 (Box 5, Folder 7)
      - Unidentified (Doerli) 1965-75 (Box 5, Folder 8)
      - Unidentifiedcirca 1963-77 (Box 5, Folder 9-10)
    - Incoming
      - A-Gcirca 1964-74 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - Ackerman, J. 1962-76 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      - Behl, Lula and Wolfgang 1968-70 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      - Braun, Louisa 1971-76 (Box 6, Folder 4)
      - Charlton, Henrietta 1962-67 (Box 6, Folder 5)
      - Drinker, Sophie 1952-66 (Box 6, Folder 6)
      - Egbers, Marlis and Gerhard 1970-76 (Box 6, Folder 7)
      - Fields, Sue 1977-75, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 8)
      - Engelbrecht, Hertha 1963-76 (Box 6, Folder 9)
      - Gans, Helene 1964-72 (Box 6, Folder 10)
      - Gerson, Tove 1968-76, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 11)
      - Glucksman, Elisabeth, circa late 1930s-75 (Box 6, Folder 12)
      - Gottschalk, Julia 1934-36, circa 1964-69 (Box 6, Folder 13)
      - H-Lcirca 1966-74 (Box 6, Folder 14)
      - Hahn, Beate 1967-70 (Box 6, Folder 15)
      - Hammerson, Gerlinde 1974-76 (Box 6, Folder 16)
      - Haupt, Gerda 1967-76 (Box 6, Folder 17)
      - Heim, Juliacirca 1964-76 (Box 6, Folder 18)
      - von Hentig, Otto 1949-76 (Box 6, Folder 19)
      - Howalt, Carola 1964-76 (Box 6, Folder 20)
      - Keiser, Hildegard 1968-70 (Box 6, Folder 21)
      - Kessel, Erna 1963-69 (Box 6, Folder 22)
      - Kuhn, Craig and Sally 1970-74 (Box 6, Folder 23)
      - Leonard, Louise 1948, circa 1965-76 (Box 6, Folder 24)
      - Lindenau, Katheleincirca 1954-74 (Box 6, Folder 25)
      - M-Zcirca 1962-74 (Box 7, Folder 1)
      - Meyer, Erna 1967-69 (Box 7, Folder 2)
      - Mombert, Francoiscirca 1965-76 (Box 7, Folder 3)
      - Mueller-Munk, Gertrude (sister) 1934, 1957-68 (Box 7, Folder 4)
      - Mueller-Munk, Peter (nephew) 1960-67 (Box 7, Folder 5)
      - Mueller-Zemmerick, Ingeberg 1963-77 (Box 7, Folder 6)
      - Munk, Ernst (brother) 1914-15 (Box 7, Folder 7)
      - Munk, Paula (mother) 1915, 1933-34 (Box 7, Folder 8)
      - Platt, Eida 1967-71 (Box 7, Folder 9)
      - Post, Clarissa 1965-71 (Box 7, Folder 10)
      - Reynolds, Elizabethcirca 1969-75 (Box 7, Folder 11)
      - Runne, Ursula 1970-76 (Box 7, Folder 12)
      - Thompson, Elizabethcirca 1950-71 (Box 7, Folder 13)
      - Yarke, Gretacirca 1950-74 (Box 7, Folder 14)
      - Zwicker, Marga 1964-75 (Box 7, Folder 15)
      - Unidentified (Doerli)circa 1969-75 (Box 7, Folder 16)
      - Unidentifiedn.d. (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Business
    - A-Dcirca 1952-73 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - E-Hcirca 1965-75 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - I-M 1937, 1965-70 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - N-Rcirca 1968-75 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - S-Zcirca 1960-73 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Re: Munk's receipt of restitution from German government 1959-56 (Box 8)
    - Re: research on institutions for delinquent girls 1933-34 (Box 8, Folder 6)
- SERIES III. WRITINGS (1915-1964)
  - Printed
    - Recht und Rechtverfolgung in Familienrecht: Eine gemeinverstaendliche darstellung fuer Unterricht und Selbststudium nebst repitorium (Verlag von Otto Liebmann, Berlin) (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Miscellaneous 1915-54 (Box 9, Folder 2-3)
    - Clippings 1924-48 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Notes
    - Marriage and familyn.d. (Box 9, Folder 5-6)
    - Miscellaneousn.d. (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Manuscripts
    - "Position of Women During and After the World War," written for the International Federation of Business and Professional Women 1940 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - "Reminiscences of a Pioneer Woman Judge in Pre-Hitler Germany: The Rise and Fall of German Feminism" (written early 1940s, before Munk took the Bar Exam in Washington, DC) 1945 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - "Can Patriotism Demand the Violent Overthrow of the Government": correspondence, notes and sources 1952 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - "Germany in the Past, America in the Present" n.d. (Box 10, Folder 4-5)
    - "The Family in Nazi Germany" n.d. (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - "Personal Rights and Mutual Obligations of Husband and Wife: chapter from "Law and Procedure of Domestic Relations" n.d. (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Miscellaneous 1931-51, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Poetryn.d. (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Speeches 1912-64 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - "Elements of Love and Marriage"
      - Table of contents and introduction 1950 (Box 11, Folder 1)
      - Parts I-IV (Chapters 1-34)n.d. (Box 11, Folder 2-6)
      - Fragments, including introduction to a 1952 edition 1952, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 7-8)
      - Correspondence 1939-57 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Writings by othersn.d. (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous poems (possibly by Munk) 1937, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 11)
- SERIES IV. SUBJECTS (1918-1959)
  - "Proposal for the Reunification of West and East Berlin" 1948 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Domestic Relations (Chicago Municipal Court) 1944 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Illegitimacy (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Juvenile Delinquency
    - Lancaster School for Girls 1947 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - New York State Training School for Girls 1934, 1959 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Lecture material 1939, 1955 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Marriage 1947, 1950 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Marriage counselingn.d. (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Psychology (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Sweden: women and families 1946-49 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Uniform Divorce Act 1954 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Germany: women (includes manuscript by Kathelein Lindenau about women during World War I and the postwar period) 1925-37 (Box 12, Folder 12)
- SERIES V. ORGANIZATIONS (1931-1974)
  - American Association of University Women, American Bar Association, German Federation of Business, and Professional Women and International Federation of Business and Professional Women 1931-74 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - International Federation of Women Lawyers 1960-74 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - League of Women Voters, Massachusetts Bar Association, National Association of Women Lawyers, National Federation of Business and Professional Women's Clubs 1960-75 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - National Conference on Family Relations 1941-47 (Box 13, Folder 4)